Well, I'm glad to have you in here today Aaron for our deep learning engineer position.
Aaron さん、深層学習エンジニア職への応募ありがとうございます。
To get started, I'd like to ask you a question
まずは深層学習について
actually in deep learning, are you ready to go?
質問させていただきますが、よろしいですか
Yeah, sure let's do it.
もちろんです。よろしくお願いします
All right. So, the first thing I'd like to ask you
ではまず、セマンティックセグメンテーションの
is just to explain the concept of semantic segmentation.
概念を説明してもらえますか
Oh sure. I've done some work on semantic segmentation.
分かりました。セマンティックセグメンテーションは経験があります。
Awesome.
素晴らしい。
I've generated some really cool results.
素晴らしい成果も挙げました
Nice.
いいですね
So, I can tell you what I've done before is I've used a fully convolution neural network,
私の成果の前に、完全な畳み込みニューラルネットワークの使用経験
and it's made up of an encoder and a decoder.
さらにエンコーダーとデコーダーの作成についてお話します
Your encoder, you can actually use transfer learning.
エンコーダーは学習内容を転送するために使用できます
So, it's just a convolution neural network.
これは畳み込みニューラルネットワークです
You can use a pre-trained one like VGG
VGG 16 のようなトレーニング済みのものを使うことも可能で
16 and then you can do some pretty interesting techniques.
さらに非常に興味深いテクニックも使用できます
So, you could use one by
デコーダーに転送するために
one convolution to bring it to a decoder and this is where things get really
畳み込みを一つずつ使用できます。そしてここがとても興味深いところなんですが
interesting because now you're using something called D
デコンボリューション層と呼ばれるものを使って
convolutional layers to actually upsample the results.
結果をアップサンプリングします
So, the result that you end up getting is the same dimensions as your input.
最終的に取得する結果は、入力したものと同じ寸法になります
So, if we're looking at trying to figure
画像のどのピクセルが道路に属し
out which pixels in an image belong to the road and which ones don't,
どのピクセルが属していないかを調べる場合など
this is where a fully convolution neural network will do great,
畳み込みニューラルネットワークが得意とする分野です
because it'll actually provide us
これを使えば道路に実際に属するピクセルがどれで
which of those pixels are actually the road and which ones aren't.
どれが属さないかを教えてくれます
So, it's looking at the category of them.
これは、それらのカテゴリーを見ています。
In order to do this,
これを実現するために
it's actually going to start out quite random when you feed in your image.
イメージをフィードする場合、かなりランダムに開始します
It's just going to look like a lot of noise.
このようにノイズが多く見られます
A lot of pixels are going to be various values.
多くのピクセルが多様な値を持ちます
So, we can actually have a label.
これにラベルを付けることができます
So we want to do some training here.
つまりここに学習させるわけです
So this is our input data and then this is our label.
これが入力データで、これがラベルです
So this is hand annotated.
手書きですね
Okay.
なるほど
So here, pixels that are one,
ここでピクセルが 1 であれば道路に属し
belong to the road and ones that are zeros are non-road.
0 は道路ではないことになります
So, this is what we want it to end up looking like.
最終的にはこのように見える結果が欲しいわけです
If we want to get from here to here,
こちらからこのような結果を得たい場合は
we're actually going to want to do some training.
何らかの学習をさせることが必要です
So, we want to have a good loss function in order to do this.
そのためには優れた損失関数が必要です
Great. What kind of loss function do you think you'll use?
そうですね。どのような損失関数が使えると思いますか
So, you can actually use a loss function that's quite similar to when you're
異なるイメージを分類する場合に使用する
just doing categories for different images.
損失関数に似たものを使用できると思います
You can use softmax and then do cross entropy and what that looks like is at first,
softmax を使った後にクロスエントロピーを実行します。どのように見えるかと言えば最初は
this is going to be quite random.
まったくランダムな状態です
So, if we just grab a pixel on here,
ここのピクセルを取得するとしたら
so there's different categories that we're dealing with.
処理する異なるカテゴリーが存在します
So, let's say that we grabbed this one that's actually a part of the road.
道路に属するこのピクセルを取得したとしましょう
So, we can have non-road and we can have road
道路でないピクセルと道路に属するピクセルを取得できます
and it is a probability that's going to sum up to one.
これは確率で合計が 1 になります
First, our network is going to produce something that doesn't sum up to one,
まずネットワークが何かを生成しますがこれは合計が 1 にはなりません
it's going to be quite random.
かなりランダムです
So, maybe we have negative 0.23 and we have 105.
たとえばマイナス 0.23 と 105 です
Well, softmax is going to be able to take this and make it into a probability.
softmax はこの数字を使って確率を出します
It ends up looking something like this function where we can use
これを関数のような形式で表し e とします
e and then we can just sum over those different values.
そして異なる値を足し合わせます
So here we have two different values and we can use that.
異なる 2 つの値があるのでこれを使用します
Make sure that it sums up to one.
そして合計が 1 になることを確認します
Okay.
分かりました
Once it actually sums up to one,
この総和が 1 になれば
we can use cross entropy and that's a log loss function and it
クロスエントロピーを使用できます。これはログ損失関数です
looks something like this where we have this negative summation and then we have,
記述すると、このように負の総和になります
let's say, is L log S where L is
そして L log S となり L はラベルの一部で
part of the label and S are the values that we're getting from the softmax.
S は softmax から取得する値です
Essentially, what that's doing is if it's actually matching up really well,
実際にうまく機能しているのであれば
it's going to be zero for the loss.
損失はゼロになります
If they're wildly off,
大きくずれている場合は
it's going to be very large and [inaudible] , large loss.
損失も大きくなります[inaudible]
So, once we actually have our loss function and this is using gradient descent and
損失関数があり、これが勾配降下法を使っているなら
following that derivative to minimize
微分係数 (デリバティブ) が損失を最小化し
the loss and then slowly over time with that training,
時間をかけてトレーニングをします
we can actually get our results that are quite noisy in random.
実際にはかなりランダムなノイズの多い結果を得ることができます
They actually look like our labels.
実物にこのラベルのように見えます
Okay. That covers everything I had on this topic anyway.
なるほど。このトピックに関する論点は網羅されたようです
Let's go ahead and move on to the next one.
では次の質問に移りましょう
Sure.
はい。